<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> </title>
    <link>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/categories/large-scale-organization/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
    <rights>(C) 2013</rights>
    <updated>2013-06-02 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>

    
      
        <item>
          <title>Obtaining Information from Federal Agencies: Tips for Complying with Touhy</title>
          <link>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2013/06/touhy-requests/</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2013/06/touhy-requests/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Subpoenaing testimony or documents from federal agencies, such as the Federal Bureau of Investigations (FBI) or Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE), is not as simple as obtaining a court order listing the materials sought. After the Supreme Court&amp;#8217;s decision in &lt;a href=&#34;http://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/340/462/case.html&#34; title=&#34;us v. touchy&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;United States v. Touhy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which held that it was a proper exercise of executive power to regulate the release of information by agency subordinates, obtaining information from a federal agency requires compliance with what is commonly known as the agency&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;T&lt;a href=&#34;http://txw.fd.org/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=VBQXlDyJUSQ%3D&amp;amp;tabid=58&#34; title=&#34;essay on touhy regs&#34;&gt;ouhy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://txw.fd.org/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=VBQXlDyJUSQ%3D&amp;amp;tabid=58&#34; title=&#34;essay on touhy regs&#34;&gt;regulations&lt;/a&gt;. Although there are ways to challenge an agency’s &lt;em&gt;Touhy&lt;/em&gt; regulations, doing so is difficult. It is usually more practical to comply with them. Here are some tips on how to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each agency has its own set of regulations. The first step in obtaining the information sought is determining &lt;strong&gt;which agency&amp;#8217;s regulations are applicable&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, smaller agencies, such as the FBI and ICE, fall under larger executive agencies: the Department of Justice and the Department of Homeland Security, respectively. &lt;strong&gt;Reach out informally to the appropriate official&lt;/strong&gt; to notify the agency of the anticipated request and seek guidance on the proper form for the request and to whom it should be directed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations or procedures generally require &lt;strong&gt;a letter request&lt;/strong&gt; to the appropriate agency official—frequently the United States Attorney, but perhaps the agency’s Office of General Counsel—accompanied by a subpoena. The letter is the most crucial part of the package. It serves to establish for the agency the relevancy of the information sought, belying concerns that it is over-inclusive and designed as part of a “fishing expedition.” It also can serve as evidence in a subsequent enforcement proceeding of the subpoena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a brief paragraph explaining who you represent, the purpose of the letter and the nature of the case, the letter should include a statement of the facts. The &lt;strong&gt;facts&lt;/strong&gt; should be written to emphasize the case’s public importance and provide a basis to conclude that the government agency has relevant information. While the facts should be written in a favorable light to your client, they might take a more neutral tone than what would be appropriate for a brief. Writing as though facts have been established or are clear defeats the purpose of a request to obtain information to support those facts. If the case has survived certain procedural hurdles that have tested the issues, such as a motion to dismiss, and narrowed the claims and parties, mention so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;requests&lt;/strong&gt; should be narrowly tailored to the extent possible and clearly state the relevance of the requested material to the claims. Avoid broad requests that are more appropriate for regular federal discovery requests. To highlight the relevancy, list the particular request and then immediately explain how that information bears on the claims at issue. Explain the relevance for each request individually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once there is a draft &lt;em&gt;Touhy&lt;/em&gt; request, it might be worthwhile to share it with the executive agency official before finalizing and submitting it. The agency might be able to immediately identify materials that it will not produce, or provide further guidance on the information or tailoring necessary to obtain at least a subset of the requested materials.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Persuasively Framing Issues</title>
          <link>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2011/11/framing-issues/</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2011/11/framing-issues/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently thought long and hard about how to frame a legal issue of first impression for a bench memorandum. The way the issue was framed would not necessarily affect the outcome of the particular case before the court. But the case&amp;#8211;and the opinion&amp;#8211;will lay the foundation for the next case in one way or another, and neither way is inherent in the existing precedent.  Although the decision is ultimately not mine, how the issue was framed at the initial stage could color how it is perceived by the judges and the nuances of the resulting opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, this exercise was a reminder of the importance of carefully framing the issue in persuasive legal writing. It is the reader&amp;#8217;s first impression of how compelling the argument is and the legitimacy of the writer. Framing the issue is relevant beyond the &amp;#8221;Issues Presented&amp;#8221; section of a brief or memo and the way it is done should be consistent throughout. The issue is the point of the piece and will be repeated, each time, hopefully, with an additional reason why the reader should be convinced of the argument. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of framing the issue as constructing a telescope through which the entire argument will be viewed and positioning the telescope in the direction of where you want the reader to end up.  Like the lens of the telescope, the issue should be clear.  Be accurate, deliberate and concise in your word choice. Negatives should be avoided when possible. For example, &amp;#8220;the right to be free from employment discrimination is well-established&amp;#8221; is better than &amp;#8220;the right to not be discriminated against in employment is well-established.&amp;#8221;  Think about the connotations of each word and if there is another word that makes your argument more appealing, perhaps because your position makes common sense when framed a particular way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A well-framed issue can also help keep the telescope pointed in the direction you want to reader to go. If there are compelling facts that a reader might empathize with, those can be included. For example &amp;#8220;the BIA violated petitioner&amp;#8217;s due process rights by failing to consider that he is a single father of four and the sole wage earner in his household&amp;#8221; is better than &amp;#8220;the BIA violated petitioner&amp;#8217;s due process rights by not granting him a waiver.&amp;#8221;  The issue should also be framed to make the court comfortable with the broader implications of ruling in your favor. Take the recent oral argument in the Supreme Court (a nice summary is &lt;a href=&#34;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/16/reasonable-expectations/?scp=3&amp;amp;sq=greenhouse&amp;amp;st=cse&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) as an example, where the many of the Justices expressed concern that GPS tracking could be used on members of the Court if they ruled in favor of the Government. We will see where the discomfort leads them, but it shows that emotion is involved in judicial decision-making, regardless of how much it is repressed. The way an issue is framed can manipulate that emotion in favor of the argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Properly framing the issue has the added bonus of assisting with the writing process. By spending some time to think about the issue and its nuances, the writer becomes more familiar with the argument before significant writing has begun. A well-articulated issue also helps focus the writer and assist with large-scale organization. It can serve as a guidepost as the argument unfolds to ensure that each piece relates to the others. That said, the specific articulation of the issue might evolve as the argument develops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it is rare that legal writing has much relevance to real life, but, as a nod to the upcoming Thanksgiving holiday when many in United States reflect on what we have to be thankful for, I will mention that framing the issue is easily applied to life. Even life&amp;#8217;s trials, if framed differently, can be positives for which to be grateful. Some small examples&amp;#8211; frustrated by your commute home from work? Be grateful you have work and a home. Tired of being tired? Be grateful of how productive you are. If it is natural for you to view life&amp;#8217;s negatives as positives, tap into that skill when framing legal issues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    

  </channel>
</rss>
