<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> </title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/legal-research/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
    <rights>(C) 2013</rights>
    <updated>2013-06-02 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>

    
      
        <item>
          <title>Obtaining Information from Federal Agencies: Tips for Complying with Touhy</title>
          <link>http://localhost:1313/2013/06/touhy-requests/</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://localhost:1313/2013/06/touhy-requests/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Subpoenaing testimony or documents from federal agencies, such as the Federal Bureau of Investigations (FBI) or Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE), is not as simple as obtaining a court order listing the materials sought. After the Supreme Court&amp;#8217;s decision in &lt;a href=&#34;http://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/340/462/case.html&#34; title=&#34;us v. touchy&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;United States v. Touhy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which held that it was a proper exercise of executive power to regulate the release of information by agency subordinates, obtaining information from a federal agency requires compliance with what is commonly known as the agency&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;T&lt;a href=&#34;http://txw.fd.org/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=VBQXlDyJUSQ%3D&amp;amp;tabid=58&#34; title=&#34;essay on touhy regs&#34;&gt;ouhy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://txw.fd.org/LinkClick.aspx?fileticket=VBQXlDyJUSQ%3D&amp;amp;tabid=58&#34; title=&#34;essay on touhy regs&#34;&gt;regulations&lt;/a&gt;. Although there are ways to challenge an agency’s &lt;em&gt;Touhy&lt;/em&gt; regulations, doing so is difficult. It is usually more practical to comply with them. Here are some tips on how to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each agency has its own set of regulations. The first step in obtaining the information sought is determining &lt;strong&gt;which agency&amp;#8217;s regulations are applicable&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, smaller agencies, such as the FBI and ICE, fall under larger executive agencies: the Department of Justice and the Department of Homeland Security, respectively. &lt;strong&gt;Reach out informally to the appropriate official&lt;/strong&gt; to notify the agency of the anticipated request and seek guidance on the proper form for the request and to whom it should be directed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regulations or procedures generally require &lt;strong&gt;a letter request&lt;/strong&gt; to the appropriate agency official—frequently the United States Attorney, but perhaps the agency’s Office of General Counsel—accompanied by a subpoena. The letter is the most crucial part of the package. It serves to establish for the agency the relevancy of the information sought, belying concerns that it is over-inclusive and designed as part of a “fishing expedition.” It also can serve as evidence in a subsequent enforcement proceeding of the subpoena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a brief paragraph explaining who you represent, the purpose of the letter and the nature of the case, the letter should include a statement of the facts. The &lt;strong&gt;facts&lt;/strong&gt; should be written to emphasize the case’s public importance and provide a basis to conclude that the government agency has relevant information. While the facts should be written in a favorable light to your client, they might take a more neutral tone than what would be appropriate for a brief. Writing as though facts have been established or are clear defeats the purpose of a request to obtain information to support those facts. If the case has survived certain procedural hurdles that have tested the issues, such as a motion to dismiss, and narrowed the claims and parties, mention so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;requests&lt;/strong&gt; should be narrowly tailored to the extent possible and clearly state the relevance of the requested material to the claims. Avoid broad requests that are more appropriate for regular federal discovery requests. To highlight the relevancy, list the particular request and then immediately explain how that information bears on the claims at issue. Explain the relevance for each request individually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once there is a draft &lt;em&gt;Touhy&lt;/em&gt; request, it might be worthwhile to share it with the executive agency official before finalizing and submitting it. The agency might be able to immediately identify materials that it will not produce, or provide further guidance on the information or tailoring necessary to obtain at least a subset of the requested materials.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Revelations in Research: At What Point Does a Dissenting Opinion Become the Majority Rule?</title>
          <link>http://localhost:1313/2012/03/revelations-research-point-dissenting-opinion-majority-rule/</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://localhost:1313/2012/03/revelations-research-point-dissenting-opinion-majority-rule/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the inspiration and encouragement from a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blhny.com/attorney.cfm/ID/23&#34;&gt;colleague&lt;/a&gt;, I embarked on writing a law journal article about women&amp;#8217;s fundamental constitutional rights that are implicated at the intersection of family-wage work structures and women&amp;#8217;s dual role as wage earner and primary family caregiver. In the article, I argue that family-wage work structures (structures developed around a worker without family caregiving responsibilities) are in part to blame for the stagnant progress that has marked workplace gender equality since the mid-1990s. The article proposes litigation strategies for removing family-wage barriers to women&amp;#8217;s equal opportunity in employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the many questions and issues that I have confronted throughout the process of writing this article, one was the role of litigation in a law and social change agenda. In the article, I wanted to argue that litigation has a necessary role to play in removing family-wage barriers to employment (in conjunction with other cause-lawyering tools, such as policy, consensus-building, and grassroots organizing). But the role of litigation in social change&amp;#8211;how effective it is, whether it should be used at all in light of the risks and resources at stake&amp;#8211;is an issue that I constantly struggle with. And, admittedly, when I sat down to write this part of the article, I was in a &amp;#8220;down on litigation&amp;#8221; mood and doubtful about whether I could come up with a convincing argument that litigation should be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lucky for the article, what emerged from my research swayed me. One of the reasons why is a matter of rudimentary legal history. I identified principals in court opinions not authored by the majority that slowly made their way into the status quo. The Equal Pay Act, for example, was inspired by a dissenting opinion by Justice Ginsburg. I also found that sometimes a concurrence from decades ago is the opinion that more accurately reflects the current state of the law than that which was espoused by the majority at the time. That was the case with the &amp;#8220;sex-plus&amp;#8221; theory of liability under Title VII, first recognized (after several failed attempts) in a 1971 case which left open the possibility that the parental status of women, but not men, could be considered in making employment decisions. Justice Marshall&amp;#8217;s concurrence rejected this notion and is more representative of the law today. And one of my favorite discoveries was this quote in a 1969 5th Circuit dissenting opinion from a denial of &lt;em&gt;en banc&lt;/em&gt; review: &amp;#8220;A mother is still a woman. And if she is denied work outright because she is a mother, it is because she is a woman.&amp;#8221; The principle behind this dissenting sentiment is directly on point with what I hope courts will eventually recognize when advocates pursue constitutional claims challenging family-wage barriers. Forty years later, in 2009, Justices Breyer and Ginsburg quoted this 5th Circuit dissent in their own dissenting opinion. While it is still not a part of a majority opinion or statute, it has arguably been elevated from a Circuit dissent on a discretionary procedural issue to a dissenting opinion by Supreme Court Justices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research brought dissenting and concurring opinions to the fore of my attention and peaked my interest in more closely examining their value and the role they play in shaping the law. In the examples just cited, if the majority opinions are accepted as the present state of the law, the concurrences or dissents are brief, perhaps imperfect, snapshots into the future of the law. But what about the dissenting opinions that emerge when the majority adopts what used to be a dissent? In that light, surely dissenting opinions are as frequently a reflection of the law&amp;#8217;s past incarnations as its future ones. Dissenting and concurring opinions are not statements of law, and have little, if any persuasive value. But in addition to providing a different perpsective, they help put a debate in a historical and political context. They can provide important insight into where the law on any particular topic has been, where it is going or could go, and how litigation contributes to its development. After all, litigation gives the court an opportunity to reconsider, refine, or reform the law as it applies to a current reality.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    

  </channel>
</rss>
