<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> </title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/nuts-and-bolts/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
    <rights>(C) 2013</rights>
    <updated>2012-07-11 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>

    
      
        <item>
          <title>Relative Clauses: Restrictive &amp; Nonrestrictive</title>
          <link>http://localhost:1313/2012/07/relative-clauses-restrictive-nonrestrictive/</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://localhost:1313/2012/07/relative-clauses-restrictive-nonrestrictive/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;A clause is a group of related words that contains a subject and a verb. It is distinguished from a phrase, which is simply a group of related words. A clause can be independent, meaning it could be its own sentence. For example, &amp;#8220;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;The statute&amp;#8217;s language is vague&lt;/span&gt;.&amp;#8221; A clause could also be dependent, meaning it depends on an independent clause for its meaning. For example, &amp;#8221;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Because the statute&amp;#8217;s language is vague&lt;/span&gt;, it is unconstitutional.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relative clauses are a type of dependant clause and are introduced by a relative pronoun (which, that, who, whichever, whoever, whom, whomever, and of which). The relative pronoun is the subject of the clause&amp;#8217;s verb. Relative clauses might be restrictive or nonrestrictive. A nonrestrictive clause is not essential to the sentence&amp;#8217;s meaning and can be removed without significantly altering it. Conversely, a restrictive clause restricts or limits the noun it modifies. When the clause should be nonrestrictive, precede it with &amp;#8220;which&amp;#8221; and set it off with commas. When the clause should be restrictive, precede it with &amp;#8220;that.&amp;#8221;  For example, the sentence &amp;#8221;Possession of the firearms, which are operable, is illegal&amp;#8221; has a different meaning than &amp;#8220;Possession of the firearms that are operable is illegal.&amp;#8221; In the latter, possession of only the operable firearms is illegal and the existence of other inoperable firearms is contemplated. In the former, the use of a nonrestrictive clause indicates that all of the firearms are operable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a relative clause modifies a person, &amp;#8220;who&amp;#8221; is used. Whether the clause that follows &amp;#8220;who&amp;#8221; is nonrestrictive or restrictive depends on whether the clause is set off with commas. For example, &amp;#8220;Joan&amp;#8217;s friend, who was in the car, is liable,&amp;#8221; (nonrestrictive) versus &amp;#8220;Joan&amp;#8217;s friend who was in the car is liable&amp;#8221; (restrictive). The nonrestrictive clause indicates that Joan has only one friend;  the restrictive clause signifies that Joan&amp;#8217;s other friends were not liable. It would be improper to state, &amp;#8220;Joan&amp;#8217;s friend, who was in the car, is liable, but the others were not,&amp;#8221; because use of the nonrestrictive clause indicates that no other friends exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, however, whether a clause should be restrictive or nonrestrictive is up to the writer and based on the meaning that the writer wants to convey. The writer must make sure that the sentence conveys the precise meaning by closely examining whether a clause should be restrictive or nonrestrictive. It is also important to examine whether clauses are restrictive or nonrestrictive when interpreting and applying statutory language and caselaw. The subtle differences in meaning between restrictive and nonrestrictive clauses are opportunities  to make legal arguments that support a position or undermine an opponent&amp;#8217;s.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>My Latest Pet Peeve: “Not Only . . . But Also . . .”</title>
          <link>http://localhost:1313/2012/06/not-only-but-also/</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://localhost:1313/2012/06/not-only-but-also/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Lately, I have been sensitive to and particularly irked by a common sentence construction: &amp;#8220;not only &amp;hellip; but also &amp;hellip; .&amp;#8221;  For example, &amp;#8220;not only was the juror related to the defense counsel, but she was also friends with the defendant&amp;#8221; or  &amp;#8220;not only did the district court abuse its discretion, but it also committed plain error.&amp;#8221; &amp;#8221;Not only &amp;hellip; but also &amp;hellip;&amp;#8221;  is used when the writer wants to emphasize a particular point, or exaggerate the many factors that favor a particular position. But it has the opposite result. The wordiness detracts from the persuasiveness. And it phrases the positive in the negative. Isn&amp;#8217;t it better to simply state, &amp;#8220;the juror was related to the defense counsel and friends with the defendant&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8221;the district court committed plain error,&amp;#8221; or even &amp;#8220;the district court did not just abuse its discretion, it committed plain error&amp;#8221;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Not only &amp;hellip; but also &amp;hellip;&amp;#8221; is used commonly in speech as well. At the moment, I am too biased against the phrase to opine as to whether it is appropriate there, but at least its delivery is packaged with a particular intonation and pace that perhaps makes it okay. Regardless, the fact that this phrase is commonly used in speech helps in understanding why I have seen it pop up in writings time again.  When I catch myself tempted to use the phrase, it is because I am transcribing my thoughts as I would say them out loud&amp;#8211;the likely reason most writers use the phrase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that light, the prevalence of the phrase in writing is an example of how certain phrases that we use in speech are so ingrained in our mode of expression that we take them for granted when we start writing. There is no problem with transcribing thoughts as you would speak them to write a first draft. In fact, &amp;#8220;writing how you speak&amp;#8221; is sometimes considered an important tactic for clear writing and avoiding legalese. But transcribed speech should be refined to clear and precise writing through editing. The presence of &amp;#8221;not only &amp;hellip; but also &amp;hellip;&amp;#8221; in a final draft is not necessarily indicative of a poorly written piece. But the phrase is a remnant of transcribed speech that should have been weeded out during editing to create a sharper statement. That and similar phrases or constructions are not good legal writing, let alone the best. Yet, their familiarity allows them to go unnoticed and survive editing. Thorough editing means identifying the common modes of expression which we take for granted and then critically examining whether using them is the most precise, concise, and persuasive way to express the point.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Footnotes &amp; When They Can Be Used for Case Citations</title>
          <link>http://localhost:1313/2012/04/footnotes/</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://localhost:1313/2012/04/footnotes/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Footnotes in legal writing generally serve at least one of three purposes: 1) they provide authority for assertions and principles, 2) they give credit to the ideas of others, 3) they add peripheral or tangential commentary to the primary argument. No matter what appears in a footnote, its significance to the overall piece is diminished simply because of its physical place on the page. Its impact is diminished by the fact that it might never be read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While footnotes have a substantial place in scholarly legal writing (although, perhaps, &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholarship.law.duke.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=2938&amp;amp;context=faculty_scholarship&amp;amp;sei-redir=1&amp;amp;referer=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com%2Furl%3Fsa%3Dt%26rct%3Dj%26q%3Dusing%2520footnotes%2520in%2520legal%2520writing%26source%3Dweb%26cd%3D8%26ved%3D0CFcQFjAH%26url%3Dhttp%253A%252F%252Fscholarship.law.duke.edu%252Fcgi%252Fviewcontent.cgi%253Farticle%253D2938%2526context%253Dfaculty_scholarship%26ei%3DxaxzT-foLabY0QGk6Mn_Ag%26usg%3DAFQjCNGCVd6l_4nshpnAxAELYioArE___w%26sig2%3D_fKemt78bBbRqoFCpv6FUA#search=%22using%20footnotes%20legal%20writing%22&#34; title=&#34;footnotes in scholarly writing&#34;&gt;a less significant place that what was previously thought&lt;/a&gt;), they should be conservatively used in briefs, memoranda, letters, or other law practice writings. Using footnotes differently in each of these types of legal writings is a function of the audience and the purpose of the writing. For example, a law journal article is equally intended to convey a persuasive argument, contribute to a debate, and spark further conversation. Readers are less interested, at least initially, in where the writer&amp;#8217;s idea came from, so long as the writing in the body is persuasive. Footnotes in scholarly research provide a compact, easily identifiable, bibliography for an interested reader. To the extent that footnotes in law journal articles contain peripheral or tangential commentary, including it in the text would distract and detract from the larger point. Including them at all might plant a seed for further scholarship, or acknowledge a seed that led to the particular principle footnoted. And footnotes are legitimate vehicles through which a writer can point out the limits of the article&amp;#8217;s subject matter or the argument without distracting the reader from the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But writings such as briefs and memoranda are primarily intended to persuade the reader of a particular argument or provide an in-depth analysis of the law. In these writings, resorting to footnoting an idea should be scrutinized. If the footnote contains a tangential or peripheral comment, consider if it  should be either altogether excluded or contained in the main text and addressed directly. Footnotes can become a crutch for a writer who cannot fully abandon all of the noise surrounding a crisp argument. Conversely, footnotes might be used to raise an argument without fulfilling the expectation and duty to fully articulate support for it. When I am tempted to footnote an idea, the first question I ask is &amp;#8220;if the idea is important enough to be included in the piece at all, why shouldn&amp;#8217;t it be in the body of the piece?&amp;#8221; I try to work the idea into the body of the piece before deciding that it belongs in a footnote. Sometimes the exercise of working it into the body reveals that it is important enough to warrant its own paragraph. Sometimes the exercise reveals that it should not be included at all. And sometimes, of course, there is a reason why the idea should be in a footnote. For example, an appellee might use a footnote to point out that an appellant had included an issue in its &amp;#8220;Statement of Issues&amp;#8221; section of the brief, but had not actually briefed the issue, rendering the issue not properly raised on appeal. The appellee might want to show the court that it was not overlooking this issue and explain why it would not be addressed. Including this footnote&amp;#8217;s substance in the body would actually be somewhat inconsistent with what the footnote was setting forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, whether something belongs in a footnote should be determined against a backdrop of a conservative use of footnotes. Think about how important the principle is, why it is necessary at all, and what it adds/the purpose it has to the overall argument. Relegating less important, but not unimportant, aspects of an argument to footnotes better leverages different parts of a writing for overall persuasion. These principles are equally applicable when considering whether citations to legal authority belong in footnotes. The debate around where citations to legal authority should appear is premised on drawing lines based on the type of authority, rather than the purpose of particular parts of a document. There is no reason why some citations to authority can appear in the body and others are better suited for footnotes. Because case law&amp;#8211;and whether it is recent, or from an appellate or trial court, or a court outside the jurisdiction&amp;#8211;determines the persuasiveness of an argument, most citations to authority should  be included in the text. Developments in law directly build on the law that already exists. When I read briefs and opinions, I am interested in a citation immediately after reading a principle. It gives me insight into how seriously I should take a particular proposition, at least initially. But there are occasions where citations to case law are properly included in a footnote. A string cite, for instance, that alerts the court to non-binding authority, but authority that highlights examples of how courts have analyzed comparable fact patterns, might be properly included in a footnote. Or a citation to a firmly established principle might appear in a footnote. Instead of strictly adhering to a rule for or against legal citations in footnotes, carefully considering each citation&amp;#8217;s place on the page means carefully considering its role  and leads to more nuanced and precise argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Using Tools of Visual Persuasion in Legal Writing</title>
          <link>http://localhost:1313/2011/12/tools-visual-persuasion-legal-writing/</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://localhost:1313/2011/12/tools-visual-persuasion-legal-writing/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I always find it difficult to read TEXT IN ALL CAPITAL LETTERS. Now I know I am not alone.  Here is an interesting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ca7.uscourts.gov/rules/painting_with_print.pdf&#34; title=&#34;visual persuasion&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://camlaw.rutgers.edu/bio/958&#34; title=&#34;Prof. Robbins Bio&#34;&gt;Professor Ruth Anne Robbins&lt;/a&gt; about tools of visual persuasion in legal writing. Professor Robbins makes the point that how a piece of legal writing looks makes it easier to read and can, therefore, influence its persuasiveness. Professor Robbins bases her thesis on the results psychological studies about reading and readability. An argument presented in a visually effective manner is better understood and retained by a reader. It might also bolster the credibility of the writer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to her #1 recommendation not to use all capital letters, some of the suggestions Professor Robbins has are 1) contrasting the font used in the text with that in the headings by using a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/serif&#34; title=&#34;serif&#34;&gt;serif&lt;/a&gt; font for text (like Times New Roman) and a [I always find it difficult to read TEXT IN ALL CAPITAL LETTERS. Now I know I am not alone.  Here is an interesting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ca7.uscourts.gov/rules/painting_with_print.pdf&#34; title=&#34;visual persuasion&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://camlaw.rutgers.edu/bio/958&#34; title=&#34;Prof. Robbins Bio&#34;&gt;Professor Ruth Anne Robbins&lt;/a&gt; about tools of visual persuasion in legal writing. Professor Robbins makes the point that how a piece of legal writing looks makes it easier to read and can, therefore, influence its persuasiveness. Professor Robbins bases her thesis on the results psychological studies about reading and readability. An argument presented in a visually effective manner is better understood and retained by a reader. It might also bolster the credibility of the writer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to her #1 recommendation not to use all capital letters, some of the suggestions Professor Robbins has are 1) contrasting the font used in the text with that in the headings by using a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/serif&#34; title=&#34;serif&#34;&gt;serif&lt;/a&gt; font for text (like Times New Roman) and a]&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/sans%20serif&#34; title=&#34;sans serif&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt; dark font for headings (like Arial); 2) cueing a hierarchy of headings with different font sizes, moving from larger to smaller; 3) creating visual chunking by adding a space between paragraphs and omitting or minimizing indentations at the first line of a paragraph; 4) keeping headings and related text close to each other; and 5) left justifying the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While individual court rules might foreclose some of these formatting suggestions, to the extent possible, lawyers should use all parts of a document, including its format, as an opportunity to persuade.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Em Dashes, Parentheses, and Commas</title>
          <link>http://localhost:1313/2011/11/em-dashes-commas-parentheses/</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://localhost:1313/2011/11/em-dashes-commas-parentheses/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Em dashes, parentheses, and commas set off parenthetical phrases in sentences. Each sets a distinct tone somewhere along the continuum of emphasis, with em dashes imparting the most emphasis to the phrase and parentheses imparting the least. Commas fall in the middle and are the most versatile of the three, minimizing interruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An em dash  temporarily shifts the focus from the main body of the sentence and signals that the phrase contained therein is meant to further illustrate the point of the sentence and, perhaps, the paragraph.  I am particularly partial to em dashes in legal writing as tools of persuasion and flow. Em dashes give the reader a moment to pause and prepare to focus on the phrase to come. If used correctly, the em dash can highlight a key concept or phrase used throughout the paragraph and help the reader draw connections leading to the conclusion.  Em dashes can also be used to reemphasize a point without being repetitive.  For example, the phrase contained within the em dashes in the following sentence restates the right the author is discussing and simultaneously qualifies the statutes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 60px;&#34;&gt;
  It is well-established that the EPC protects the right to equal employment opportunity regardless of gender. Indeed, Title VII and the Family Medical Leave Act (“FMLA”)—two federal statutes with the goal of achieving equal employment opportunity for women—were enacted to enforce this constitutional right.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, in a sentence unavoidably long or complex, substituting commas with an em dash can eliminate confusion. Doing so also breaks up the monotony of the sentence. Take the following sentence as an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 60px;&#34;&gt;
  In both contexts, statutes—the Americans with Disabilities Act (“ADA”) and Title VII, respectively—make it an unlawful employment practice for an employer not to make reasonable accommodations, short of undue hardship, for the disabilities or religious practices of its employees.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the em dashes were replaced with commas, the sentence would be wrought with them and might cause a reader to stumble or reread the sentence. By using an em dash, the writer also signals that the reader should take note of the specific statutes to which she refers, presumably because they are somehow relevant to the overall piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, parentheses are used to signify a tangential thought that is less integral to the point of the sentence, but perhaps clarifies or comments on the main body of the sentence.  If the em dashes in the first example were replaced with parentheses,  it would seem unimportant to the argument that Title VII and FMLA are federal statutes enacted to enforce employment rights. The reader might not pay attention to this point. Likewise, replacing the em dashes with parentheses in the second example would give the impression that the specific statutes are not necessarily important, but, perhaps, interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because parentheses usually contain tangential ideas, a temptation to use parentheses in legal writing should be carefully examined.  The tangential idea contained in parentheses almost by definition has little persuasive value. Worse, it might be distracting or come off as snarky to the reader. If the idea contained in a parenthetical is important enough to be included, it probably can and should be included without parentheses so that it gets the full emphasis it deserves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, commas, the most common of these tools, seem to have an endless amount of uses. When used like em dashes or parentheses, they signal a clarification that flows smoothly from the main sentence body, to the phrase, and back to the main body again.  The phrase &amp;#8220;short of undue hardship&amp;#8221; in the first example above illustrates this. The phrase, which qualifies an employer&amp;#8217;s duty, deserves to be closely integrated with the sentence&amp;#8217;s main body. Unless the writer is trying to make the point, for instance, that an employer was unduly burdened, the phrase should also not be highlighted relative to the other parts of the sentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, which of these punctuation marks is used is determined by style and flow of the sentence and overall piece.  It requires the writer to know what should be emphasized and deemphasized and listen carefully and critically to the writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Transitions in Legal Writing</title>
          <link>http://localhost:1313/2011/10/transitions-legal-writing/</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://localhost:1313/2011/10/transitions-legal-writing/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Good legal writing seamlessly carries its reader from one idea to the next, smoothly paving the way for the reader to arrive at the ultimate conclusion. One of the most important tools for carrying the reader through an argument is the transition from one sentence or paragraph to the next.  Transitions serve as a subtle reminder to the reader of the idea that preceded it and signal an expansion of that idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often think of transitions as the link between two train cars, connecting, not only the two cars, but the entire train.  Strong transitions repeat a key word or words from the preceding sentence or paragraph and, sometimes, use a conjunction or a conjunctive phrase to join the sentences or paragraphs.  For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 90px;&#34;&gt;
  . . . . The bare allegation of property damage alone was sufficient to demonstrate a &lt;em&gt;potentially&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;covered&lt;/em&gt; claim for &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;property damage&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; cause by &amp;#8220;an &lt;em&gt;occurrence&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&#34;padding-left: 90px;&#34;&gt;
  Contrary to the District Court&amp;#8217;s holding, a &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;coverage&lt;/em&gt; was not foreclosed simply because the cross-complaint failed to contain any facts to show that the &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;property damage&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; was &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; caused by an &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;occurrence&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#8221; . . .
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the writer repeated several key terms which serve clarity and continuity. And the use of  &amp;#8221;contrary&amp;#8221; signals to the reader that the new paragraph is related to the preceding one and bolsters the repetition. Using these tools allows the reader to more easily grasp the argument and prevents them from getting distracted or confused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without strong transitions, the reader is left to create the links from one idea to the next.  Even in cases where the links are relatively apparent, the reader is disoriented and following the argument is unduly cumbersome. The extra work a reader must do to understand the argument undermines it, no matter how meritorious. Strong transitions are essential to persuasive writing because they allow a reader to arrive at the conclusion effortlessly and without distraction. Not only does this ensure that the reader understands the point, but it makes the point seem as though it is the inevitable &amp;#8212; and, perhaps, only &amp;#8212; conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Details of Persuasive Legal Writing: Choosing “And” or “But”</title>
          <link>http://localhost:1313/2011/10/and-but/</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://localhost:1313/2011/10/and-but/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;
  In the midst of writing a bench memo, I wrote the following sentence (which I have since completely changed) and struggled about whether I should use &amp;#8220;and&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8221;but&amp;#8221;:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: justify; padding-left: 60px;&#34;&gt;
  &amp;#8220;In &lt;em&gt;Sum&lt;/em&gt;, the issue before the Ninth Circuit was whether the petitioner, who was admitted into the United States at a point of entry as a lawful permanent resident &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; was only admitted as such because he misrepresented his status, was eligible to apply for a § 212(h) waiver.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It occurred to me that I often have a debate with myself over the proper use of and/but.   There are clear times when &amp;#8220;and&amp;#8221; is more appropriate, (but/and) there are clear times with &amp;#8220;but&amp;#8221; is more appropriate.  When either one might work, it seems like my default is to use &amp;#8220;but&amp;#8221; without much thinking.  But this choice deserves more attention because these words subtly communicate inclusion and exclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;And&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;but&amp;#8221; are conjunctions, meaning they link two clauses of a single sentence.  Using &amp;#8220;but&amp;#8221; in some way negates or undermines the preceding clause in favor of the succeeding one. By contrast, &amp;#8220;and&amp;#8221; tends to convey the existence of both clauses together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I chose to use &amp;#8220;and&amp;#8221; in the above sentence, I did so because the Court ultimately concluded that the petitioner was &amp;#8220;admitted&amp;#8221; as defined by the statute despite the fact that the admission was substantively unlawful (as he has misrepresented his status at the time of admission). Using &amp;#8220;and&amp;#8221; is consistent with the Court&amp;#8217;s holding that the term &amp;#8220;admitted&amp;#8221; can include substantively unlawful admissions and more accurately summarizes the decision. It also subtly leads the reader to the Court&amp;#8217;s conclusion. Had I used &amp;#8220;but,&amp;#8221; it would have negated the portion of the sentence that refers to lawful admission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this example is one where I was simply trying to most accurately summarize judicial precedent, it is easy to imagine how using &amp;#8220;and&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;but&amp;#8221; can subtly persuade.  The petitioner in &lt;em&gt;Sum&lt;/em&gt;, for example, who was arguing that his substantively unlawful admission was not an &amp;#8220;admission&amp;#8221; as defined by the statute, would be best served by using &amp;#8220;but.&amp;#8221; For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: justify; padding-left: 60px;&#34;&gt;
  &amp;#8220;Petitioner was admitted into the United States at a point of entry as a lawful permanent resident, &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; was only admitted as such because he misrepresented his status.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using &amp;#8220;but&amp;#8221; calls into question whether the petitioner was &amp;#8220;admitted&amp;#8221; as defined by the statute.  Conversely, the government would have been best served by using &amp;#8220;and.&amp;#8221; Both are proper recitations of the facts, but they subtly convey different meanings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    

  </channel>
</rss>
