<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> </title>
    <link>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/categories/theory/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
    <rights>(C) 2013</rights>
    <updated>2012-01-19 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>

    
      
        <item>
          <title>Legal Writing, Gender, and Gender-Neutral Language</title>
          <link>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2012/01/legal-writing-gender-gender-neutral-language/</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2012/01/legal-writing-gender-gender-neutral-language/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Across categories of judicial opinions, briefs, and law review articles, the use of male-gendered pronouns and generics (such as using _businessman_ instead of _businessperson_ or _layman_ instead of _layperson)_  when referring to all people is prevalent. (_See_ 16 Colum. J. Gender &amp;amp; L. 643, 661 (2007)) Experts are divided on whether the use of gendered language is appropriate. Some say that striving towards gender-neutrality in text is unduly cumbersome. Other experts, like &lt;a href=&#34;http://lawprose.org/bryan_garner/about.php&#34; title=&#34;Garner Bio&#34;&gt;Bryan A. Garner&lt;/a&gt;, argue that using gender-neutral language gives the writer credibility to a wider range of readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a proponent of  using gender-neutral language when referring to all people, particularly in legal writing. My reasons are both practical and political. I agree with Garner that using gender neutral language bolsters a writer&amp;#8217;s credibility to a wider range of readers. In part, this is because of the politics involved. American culture has taken significant steps away from the notion that &amp;#8220;she&amp;#8221; is included in &amp;#8220;he&amp;#8221;&amp;#8211;politically and socially. Readership, regardless of gender, might very well consider the use of male-gendered words a failure to reflect this social shift linguistically. It might also be offensive to a reader who interprets the use of male-gendered words to be an exclusion of all others from certain spheres, despite the writer&amp;#8217;s intent.  Similarly, unlike the times when the legal profession was only open to men, and, therefore, most readers of legal writing were men, a reader might not be a man. If not, a piece that uses male-gendered language could alienate the reader. Alienation causes any reader to disengage, hindering the writer&amp;#8217;s persuasiveness and credibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, male-gendered words, such as &amp;#8220;man&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;he&amp;#8221; are not synonymous with &amp;#8220;people&amp;#8221; and, therefore, are not the most precise word choices. The lack of precision can cause reader confusion. For example, when a writer intends to articulate a law or principle applicable to all people and uses gendered language to do so, a reader can easily be confused into thinking the writer is only referring to the particular parties at issue. Indeed, studies support the likelihood of reader confusion from the use of male-gendered words:  for most readers, using words like &amp;#8220;chairman&amp;#8221; instead of &amp;#8220;chairperson&amp;#8221; evoke images of men in those roles, not of all people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using gender-neutral language is also important from the perspective of equality. Our social reality and language are related. Seemingly innocuous language can reinforce gender stereotypes and status differences, despite the writer&amp;#8217;s intention. Using language that includes only men marginalizes and excludes the experiences of others. It symbolizes, endorses, and perpetuates gender inequality. Because the law plays a significant role in shaping the boundaries of human interaction and progress, using gender-neutral language in legal writing is a subtle, yet powerful, tool for advancing equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several techniques for avoiding gendered words that should be used in conjunction with each other. Varied and thoughtful use of the techniques will help avoid the primary criticism for using gender-neutral language: that it is cumbersome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pluralize.  &lt;/strong&gt;Instead of &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Take first an alien convicted of conspiring to distribute cocaine, whom DHS seeks to deport on the ground that he has committed an &amp;#8216;aggravated felony&amp;#8217; involving &amp;#8216;illicit trafficking in a controlled substance&amp;#8221;  &lt;/em&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Judulang v. Holder&lt;/span&gt; (slip opinion, J. Kagan)) write &lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8220;Take first  &lt;strong&gt;aliens&lt;/strong&gt; convicted of conspiring to distribute cocaine, whom DHS seeks to deport on the ground that &lt;strong&gt;they have&lt;/strong&gt; committed an &amp;#8216;aggravated felony&amp;#8217; involving &amp;#8216;illicit trafficking in a controlled substance.&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;__&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repeat the noun. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Take first an alien convicted of conspiring to distribute cocaine, whom DHS seeks to deport on the ground that &lt;strong&gt;the alien &lt;/strong&gt;has committed an &amp;#8216;aggravated felony&amp;#8217; involving &amp;#8216;illicit trafficking in a controlled substance.&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use paired pronouns. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Take first an alien convicted of conspiring to distribute cocaine, whom DHS seeks to deport on the ground that he &lt;strong&gt;or she&lt;/strong&gt; has committed an &amp;#8216;aggravated felony&amp;#8217; involving &amp;#8216;illicit trafficking in a controlled substance.&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. &lt;strong&gt;Use &amp;#8220;they&amp;#8221; as a singular pronoun.&lt;/strong&gt; This technique is only starting to gain acceptance in writing. Because it is still controversial, if you choose to use it, reserve it for instances when you know your reader well or for more causal writing. &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Take first an alien convicted of conspiring to distribute cocaine, whom DHS seeks to deport on the ground that &lt;strong&gt;they have&lt;/strong&gt; committed an &amp;#8216;aggravated felony&amp;#8217; involving &amp;#8216;illicit trafficking in a controlled substance.&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid gendered generics&lt;/strong&gt;. The implications of gendered generics sometimes go unnoticed because the use of these words is widely accepted. The most obvious gendered words are &amp;#8220;man&amp;#8221; (i.e. &amp;#8220;all men are created equal&amp;#8221;) and words containing &amp;#8220;man&amp;#8221; (i.e. mankind, man-made, mailman). Be aware of these words and replace them with gender-neutral alternatives (i.e. humankind, synthetic, mail carrier).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be consistent with how proper nouns are treated.&lt;/strong&gt;  If you refer to men by their last name, refer to women the same way. Refer to women by their full titles, just as you would with men. Use &amp;#8220;Ms.&amp;#8221; instead of &amp;#8220;Miss&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Mrs.&amp;#8221;  &amp;#8221;Ms.&amp;#8221;&amp;#8211;like &amp;#8220;Mr.&amp;#8221;&amp;#8211;does not indicate whether a person is married or single and, therefore, does not define a woman by her relation to a man.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Persuasively Framing Issues</title>
          <link>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2011/11/framing-issues/</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2011/11/framing-issues/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently thought long and hard about how to frame a legal issue of first impression for a bench memorandum. The way the issue was framed would not necessarily affect the outcome of the particular case before the court. But the case&amp;#8211;and the opinion&amp;#8211;will lay the foundation for the next case in one way or another, and neither way is inherent in the existing precedent.  Although the decision is ultimately not mine, how the issue was framed at the initial stage could color how it is perceived by the judges and the nuances of the resulting opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, this exercise was a reminder of the importance of carefully framing the issue in persuasive legal writing. It is the reader&amp;#8217;s first impression of how compelling the argument is and the legitimacy of the writer. Framing the issue is relevant beyond the &amp;#8221;Issues Presented&amp;#8221; section of a brief or memo and the way it is done should be consistent throughout. The issue is the point of the piece and will be repeated, each time, hopefully, with an additional reason why the reader should be convinced of the argument. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of framing the issue as constructing a telescope through which the entire argument will be viewed and positioning the telescope in the direction of where you want the reader to end up.  Like the lens of the telescope, the issue should be clear.  Be accurate, deliberate and concise in your word choice. Negatives should be avoided when possible. For example, &amp;#8220;the right to be free from employment discrimination is well-established&amp;#8221; is better than &amp;#8220;the right to not be discriminated against in employment is well-established.&amp;#8221;  Think about the connotations of each word and if there is another word that makes your argument more appealing, perhaps because your position makes common sense when framed a particular way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A well-framed issue can also help keep the telescope pointed in the direction you want to reader to go. If there are compelling facts that a reader might empathize with, those can be included. For example &amp;#8220;the BIA violated petitioner&amp;#8217;s due process rights by failing to consider that he is a single father of four and the sole wage earner in his household&amp;#8221; is better than &amp;#8220;the BIA violated petitioner&amp;#8217;s due process rights by not granting him a waiver.&amp;#8221;  The issue should also be framed to make the court comfortable with the broader implications of ruling in your favor. Take the recent oral argument in the Supreme Court (a nice summary is &lt;a href=&#34;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/16/reasonable-expectations/?scp=3&amp;amp;sq=greenhouse&amp;amp;st=cse&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) as an example, where the many of the Justices expressed concern that GPS tracking could be used on members of the Court if they ruled in favor of the Government. We will see where the discomfort leads them, but it shows that emotion is involved in judicial decision-making, regardless of how much it is repressed. The way an issue is framed can manipulate that emotion in favor of the argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Properly framing the issue has the added bonus of assisting with the writing process. By spending some time to think about the issue and its nuances, the writer becomes more familiar with the argument before significant writing has begun. A well-articulated issue also helps focus the writer and assist with large-scale organization. It can serve as a guidepost as the argument unfolds to ensure that each piece relates to the others. That said, the specific articulation of the issue might evolve as the argument develops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it is rare that legal writing has much relevance to real life, but, as a nod to the upcoming Thanksgiving holiday when many in United States reflect on what we have to be thankful for, I will mention that framing the issue is easily applied to life. Even life&amp;#8217;s trials, if framed differently, can be positives for which to be grateful. Some small examples&amp;#8211; frustrated by your commute home from work? Be grateful you have work and a home. Tired of being tired? Be grateful of how productive you are. If it is natural for you to view life&amp;#8217;s negatives as positives, tap into that skill when framing legal issues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>In Legal Writing, Form is Substance</title>
          <link>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2011/10/legal-writing-form-substance/</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Jill Maxwell</author>
          <guid>http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2011/10/legal-writing-form-substance/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I am following up to my mention of the dichotomy between form and substance in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jillmaxwell.com/2011/09/inaugural-post-realizing-legal-writing/&#34; title=&#34;(inaugural post) Realizing Legal Writing&#34;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt;. Substance generally refers to content and form to the style of expressing content. Especially in conversation, we sometimes slack off on finding the perfect word or tone and rely on our audience to “get the gist” of what we are trying to say or “know what we mean” despite our sloppy form.  We sacrifice form for substance. The sacrifice is sometimes appropriate and even preferred, particularly in those contexts where we have immediate feedback. But in writing, and especially in legal writing, sacrificing form sacrifices substance. The dichotomy between form and substance is almost nonexistent. It is sometimes easy to forget this simply by virtue of how we are taught legal writing. With a focus on paragraphs, sentence structure, and so forth, legal writing is often taught with little reference to substance. One consequence of this is that it leads to an assumption that form is not itself substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But meaning is gleaned from a punctuation mark, choosing one synonym over another, large-scale organization of an entire piece, and everything in between.  Confusion, disagreement, and, ultimately, litigation thrive off of alternate unintended meanings &amp;#8212; of contracts, statutes or precedent &amp;#8212; created or exposed by sloppy form. Form determines how substance will be interpreted and, therefore, its meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, form’s goal is to clearly and accurately convey substance so that it is interpreted as its intended meaning. Of course, there is no easy or straight answer as to how to do this, in part because each writing has its own context and purpose and each writer their own personality. Perhaps it includes following all grammatical rules, avoiding passive voice, and writing short sentences. But, unfortunately, clearly and accurately conveying substance it not as simple as following basic principles. And none of these, or even all of them together, is the complete recipe for good form. Rather, it takes detailed awareness, deliberate choices, and critical editing. And practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    

  </channel>
</rss>
